Guide to the Winn family papers, 1780-1925 RL.10095
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Winn family papers
1780-1925
1780-1889
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Winn family
RL.10095
5 Linear Feet 9 boxes, 2,684 items, 27 vols.
Collection contains personal and business correspondence, papers, and volumes, mainly of John Winn (d. 1844), farmer, lawyer, and postmaster, and his son, Philip James Winn, physician and postmaster of Fluvanna Co., Va., and of the Winn (Wynn) family. The papers of the elder Winn relate to bounty claims of Revolutionary veterans, personal and business affairs, and include information about "Bremo," the plantation of Gen. John Hartwell Cocke. The papers of Philip James Winn relate to his education at the Virginia Military Institute and the University of Virginia, his career in medicine, the service of his brothers in the Confederate Army, and family activities, and include a description of the religious service of the Dunkards, records of the invention and patenting of a "new gate latch," and a letter of William H. Winn describing the battles of Bethel (1861) and Gettysburg (1863). More than half the collection consists of receipts and bills connected chiefly with John Winn's work in Revolutionary bounty lands and with Philip James Winn's invention. Twenty-seven volumes include post office accounts of John Winn and of his successor, Philip James Winn; a letter book concerning the "New Gate Latch"; accounts of the estate of Samuel Kidd; letter books; ledgers; medical notes; and records of births and deaths of slaves.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Biographical Note
John Winn (d. 1844), was a farmer, lawyer, and postmaster in Fluvanna County, Virginia. His son, Philip James Winn, a graduate of the Virginia Military Institute and the University of Virginia, was a physician and also postmaster of Fluvanna County. He also served in the Confederate Army during the Civil War and was present at the Battles of Bethel (1861) and Gettysburg (1863).
Collection Overview
Family and business correspondence of John Winn (d. 1844); of his wife Lucy Winn; and of their numerous children, including Philip James Winn. The correspondence of John Winn, farmer, lawyer, postmaster at Winnsville, captain in the War of 1812, and agent for General John Hartwell Cocke, includes information on Bremo, the plantation of the latter, including also a list of periodicals subscribed to by Cocker and legal cases relative to Revolutionary bounty land.
Correspondence centering around Philip James Winn includes information on the Virginia Military Institute, Lexington, and the University of Virginia, Charlottesville, both of which he attended; one letter with a description of the unusual religious services of the Dunkards; a deed for land purchased by a free Negro; records of the invention and patenting of a 'New Gate Latch' by Philip J. Winn; and the interest of various members of the family in law, medicine, agriculture, mechanics, business, religion, and the operation of a stagecoach line between Richmond and Staunton, Virginia.
Collection also Includes a letter of William H. Winn containing detailed descriptions of the battles of Bethel, 1861, and Gettysburg, 1863, in which he participated as a Confederate soldier. More than half the collection consists of receipts and bills connected chiefly with John Winn's work in Revolutionary bounty lands and with Philip James Winn's invention. Twenty-seven volumes include post office accounts of John Winn and of his successor, Philip James Winn; a letter book concerning the 'New Gate Latch'; accounts of the estate of Samuel Kidd; letter books; ledgers; medical notes; and records of births and deaths of slaves.
Provenance
The Winn Family Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1933 and 1951.
Plantations -- Virginia; Physicians -- Virginia; Postal service -- Virginia; Postmasters; Big Bethel, Battle of, Va., 1861; Church of the Brethren -- Virginia; Gettysburg, Battle of, Gettysburg, Pa., 1863; Bounties, Military -- United States; Universities and colleges -- Virginia; Slave records -- Virginia; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Campaigns; Bremo (Va.: Estate); Winn, John; Winn, Philip James; Confederate States of America. Army; Kidd, Samuel; University of Virginia -- Students; Winn family; Virginia Military Institute -- Students
- Winn family papers, 1780-1925
  - Letters, 1780-1837; 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1837-1865; 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Letters, 1866-1925 and undated (Box 3)
  - Legal papers, bills, etc., 1770-1829; 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Legal papers, bills, etc., 1830-1838; 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Legal papers, bills, etc., 1839-1854; 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Legal papers, bills, etc., 1855-1880; 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Legal papers, bills, etc., 1881-1892 and undated; 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Drawings, printed materials, pictures, undated; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Other writings and fragments, undated; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Bound volumes (Box 9)
    Scope and Contents
    Bound volumes not itemized below are boxed together here.
  - Memoranda book, 1852-1858 (Volume S:4172)
  - Journal, 1878 (Volume M:4173)
  - Account book, 1832-1842 (Volume L:4175)
  - Account book (Post Master's), 1836 (Volume M:4176)
  - Account Book (Post Master's), 18399-1840 (Volume F:4178)
  - Account book, 1841-1842 (Volume M:4179)
  - Account book, 1870-1888 (Volume F:4181)
  - Account book, 1877-1874 (Volume L:4182)
  - Account book, 1892-1893 (Volume L:4184)
  - Day book, 1832 (Volume L:4185)
  - Letter book, 1885-1887 (Volume L:4186)
  - Ledger, 1893 (Volume L:4187)
  - Ledger, 1898-1900 (Volume L:4188)
  - Medical notes, 1883 (Volume M:4189)
  - Account book, 1833-1838 (Volume S:4190)
    Records of soldiers from Virginia who served in the War of 1812. Kept by an attorney for purposes of obtaining pensions for ex-soldiers.
  - Account book, 1853-1864 (Volume M:4193)
  - Account book, 1845 (Volume M:4196)
  - Lecture notes (Medical), 1847-1849 (Volume M:4197)
  - Ledger, 1889 (Volume L:4198)
  - Letter book, 1883-1887 (Volume L:4199)
  - Records of births and deaths of slaves, 1775-1924 (Volume S:4200)